Guide to the Dogtooth Violet collection, 1974-2019 MS 907
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Dogtooth Violet collection
1975-2019
1974-1975
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Dogtooth Violet
MS 907
2 Linear Feet (1 oversize box and 1 LP box)
This collection consists of documents, posters and audio documenting the band Dogtooth Violet.
Biographical / Historical
In 1973, Pam Grimes was playing at Sand Mountain Coffee House. Bob Oldreive approached her about joining a nascent band with his friend Bill Bertinot. Soon after the band became larger adding Joe Lindley, Richard "RJ" Jacob, and Marty Smith. The band christened themselves Dogtooth Violet and made a name for themselves playing a version of "country-rock" that was popular in the mid-1970s.
The band's lineup played a variety of instruments: Joe Lindley - fiddle, banjo, mandolin, guitar, vocals; Bob Oldreive - vocals, rhythm guitar; Bill Bertinot - lead guitar, steel guitar, dobro; Pam Grimes - vocals, washboard, guitar; Richard "RJ" Jacob - drums, vocals; Marty Smith - bass. Bob Oldreive, Pam Grimes, and Bill Bertinot wrote original music.
The band went their separate ways in 1976 with three of the members creating the band Paradise.
Since the 1980s, Dogtooth Violet has reunited to play shows in Houston at venues like Rockefeller's, Fitzgerald's, Anderson Fair Retail Restaurant, and most recently Warehouse Live. Marty Smith joined the band for most of the reunions, but passed in 2003.
Content Description
This collection contains Dogtooth Violet-related posters, documents, and audio.
Conditions Governing Access
This materials is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Bob Oldrieve and Pam Grimes in 2016 and 2019.
Related Materials
Please see Dogtooth Violet images in the Houston Folk Music collection, MS 649. See also the online exhibit: https://digitalprojects.rice.edu/houston-folk-music-archive/exhibits/show/dogtooth-violet/biography
Index Terms
Subjects
Folk music -- Texas -- Houston; Music
Document Types
Folk-rock music
- Series I: Posters
  - Papa Feelgoods poster with Greez Wheels, 1974-07-11 (Box 1)
  - Lonestar Coyote poster, 1974-11-15 (Box 1)
  - Liberty Hall poster with The Flying Burrito Brothers, 1975-02-25-1975-02-26 (Box 1)
  - Sweetheart of Texas poster featuring Spanky and Our Gang, Dogtooth Violet, Augie Meyer, Clifton Chenier, Kenneth Threadgill, Denim, 1975-03-20-1975-04-26 (Box 1)
  - Sweetheart of Texas poster featuring Alex Harvey, Dogtooth Violet, Townes Van Zandt, Bill Staines, 1975-05-01-1975-05-17 (Box 1)
  - Sweetheart of Texas poster featuring Denim, 1975-08-15-1975-08-16 (Box 1)
  - The Sweetheart of Texas, 1975-08-22-1975-08-23 (Box 1)
  - Warehouse Live, 2019-09-21 (Box 1)
- Series II: General files
  - Lyrics, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - News clippins, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series III: Audio
  - Dogtooth Violet (CD), 2019 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dogtooth Violet (LP), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)